Hello everyone and welcome to
English Pod, my name is Marco.
My name is Catherine.
What's wrong, Catherine?
Just a little down today.
You're not in the mood today, is that
what I am not in the mood to record today.
Actually, no, I am in the mood.
So we're talking about
moods, feelings, emotions.
This is today's podcast
and we're going to
be learning a lot of the names
for different kinds of feelings.
That's right.
So you're going to learn
how to describe what mood
you're in, maybe you're in a
good mood, bad mood, etc.
So let's just jump into the
dialogue and see what's going on.
Are you okay?
You seem a bit anxious.
Yeah, I'm okay.
I've been having a lot
of mood swings lately.
I think it has to do
with the pills my doctor
prescribed that are causing
chaos on my hormones.
Will you mean you feel ecstatic
one minute and then blew the next?
Yeah, it's weird.
For example, just this morning, I
was feeling detached and lonely.
Even though there was really
no reason to feel that way.
Well, maybe your mood
will swing positively
and you will feel confident,
brave and hopeful.
I hope you're right.
Okay, lots of feelings, so many feelings
and facts that we're going to talk about.
The names of them in
today's language take away.
So on language take away,
let's take a look at this adjective.
You are feeling or you seem
a little bit anxious, anxious.
He is anxious.
I feel anxious.
That's right.
Now, this word means that you're
feeling nervous or uneasy about something.
Normally when you feel
anxious about something
like a test, all you can
think about is the test.
Right.
So, if you're anxious,
you're worried about
something or you're
nervous about something.
It could be about your job,
interview a test, et cetera.
All right.
So, moving on now,
we're feeling anxious, but
then we also feel a
different type of excitement.
We are ecstatic.
All right.
So, while anxious is a bad feeling,
ecstatic is a really good feeling.
Okay.
So, I'm happy.
I'm really happy.
I'm ecstatic.
That's a really, really,
really happy feeling.
Okay.
So, if you're ecstatic, it
means you're very, very happy.
So, it's not a negative thing.
No.
So, when I get 100%
on my test, I'm ecstatic.
I'm really happy.
Okay.
Now, basically the complete opposite of
being ecstatic would be to feel or be blue.
Yeah.
This might seem a bit strange because
blue is a color, as you know, B-L-U-E.
But when you're feeling blue means that
you're feeling sad or down or out of sad.
Yeah.
So, maybe this is why you
also have music, the blues, right?
The blues.
He's got the blues.
That means he's sad about
something, usually a woman.
Uh-huh.
Okay.
So, ecstatic, very, very happy
feeling blue, very, very sad.
And, uh, well, another
example of feelings,
also a negative one is if
you feel detached, detached.
Mm-hmm.
Alright.
So, we know the word "attached,"
that means to put two things together.
Well, detached means
to take two things apart.
Okay.
So, what do you feel apart from?
Other people.
Uh-huh.
Okay.
So, for example, if I'm
feeling detached, maybe
it means that I don't
feel like the people
around me understand
me, I don't want to talk to
other people, I'm just
not feeling very social.
So, for example, can you feel
detached in your relationship?
You can, and that's
actually really bad feeling
because you should be
happy in a relationship.
Right.
But when you're detached, it
means that you don't really feel
close to your boyfriend or
girlfriend or husband or wife.
Okay.
And, we feel detached
and lonely, so if you
feel lonely, that means
that you feel similar
to detached, lonely means that you
don't feel like you can talk to anyone.
You feel alone.
So, I'm very lonely right now.
I have no one to talk to, no friends,
you know, no one makes me feel good.
Okay.
So, that means that you feel alone.
All right.
A lot of adjectives,
there are many different
ways to describe
the way that you feel.
So, let's take a listen
to the dialogue again.
Are you okay, you seem a bit anxious?
Yeah, I'm okay.
I've been having a lot
of mood swings lately.
I think it has to do
with the pills my doctor
prescribed that are causing
chaos on my hormones.
So, you mean you feel ecstatic
one minute and then blew the next?
Yeah, it's weird.
For example, just this morning, I
was feeling detached and lonely.
You know there was really
no reason to feel that way.
Well, maybe your mood
will swing positively
and you will feel confident,
brave and hopeful.
I hope you're right.
All right, we're back.
So now let's take a
look at fluency builder.
Fluency builder.
So on fluency builder today,
the first phrase is mood swings.
Mm-hmm.
I've been having a lot
of mood swings lately.
That's right.
So this basically means that your
mood is changing constantly all the time.
That's right.
So your mood is the way that you feel
and to swing means to go back and forth.
So I'm happy.
I'm sad.
I'm angry.
I'm, you know, lazy.
So these are mood swings and
it means that you're not normal.
You're not flat.
You're going up and down
and feeling many different things.
Okay, so to be clear, also,
mood, your mood is the
way that you feel at a
certain time or a certain day.
That's right.
So you're in a good mood today.
Did you get good news?
That's right.
So that means that you
look like you are happy
or it seems that your
personality is positive today.
That's right.
Or you could say, I'm in a bad mood.
Don't talk to me.
So you're maybe you're angry.
Yeah.
All right.
Very good.
So to basically explain
why we're having these
mood swings, we say
that well, maybe it has
to do with the pills, the doctor prescribed
that are causing chaos on my hormones.
All right.
Chaos is a thing.
It's a noun.
And chaos means that there's no order.
Everything is crazy.
It's out of control.
And so basically what this person is saying
is that the pills that he's taking, it can
feel out of control.
Right.
So they are causing chaos to cause
chaos, to cause nothing in control.
And on your hormones, but what does
hormones have to do with your mood?
All right.
Hormones are chemicals that
your body actually produces.
Women have different hormones from
men, but they affect the way that we feel.
So oftentimes you could say that I'm
in a bad mood because of my hormones.
Right.
Pregnant women are very famous for
having mood swings, happy, sad, angry.
Because they have more hormones
in their bodies that they're not used to.
Right.
And so they cannot control
the way that they feel.
That's right.
So an example is if a
man has too much of one
hormone, like testosterone
is a hormone, then
this person will usually
be very aggressive, right?
That's right.
And the female counterpart
to testosterone is estrogen.
So if you have too much estrogen,
maybe you'll be a little bit too sensitive.
Or emotional.
That's right.
Okay.
So that's what we talk
about chaos and hormones.
Now, when we talked about mood
swings, we take it as a noun, right?
You have mood swings.
But then at the end
of the dialogue, we'll
see, we say, well, maybe your
mood will swing positively.
So now we're talking, it's separate.
It's not a noun.
We're taking swing as a verb.
To swing.
That means think about
pendulum, you know,
and clock because left
and then swings, right?
Right.
We could talk about a mood like this.
So maybe your bad mood will swing the other
way, maybe it will become a good mood.
And so to swing here is the verb, okay,
maybe try and encourage your mood to swing.
Okay.
So to be clear, mood swings are a noun.
But then in this last part,
we put the verb to swing
to kind of explain where
mood swings comes from, right?
So the noun mood swings, now you understand
that it's kind of like a pendulum and it's
swinging back and forth and
you're changing constantly.
Exactly.
All right.
So let's take a listen to
the dialogue one last time.
Are you okay?
You seem a bit anxious.
Yeah.
I'm okay.
I've been having a lot
of mood swings lately.
I think it has to do
with the pills my doctor
prescribed that are causing
chaos on my hormones.
So you mean you feel ecstatic
one minute and then blew the next?
Yeah.
It's weird.
Well, just this morning, I was
feeling detached and lonely.
You know, there was really
no reason to feel that way.
Well, maybe your mood
will swing positively
and you will feel confident,
brave and hopeful.
I hope you're right.
All right.
So talking about moods,
now there are certain,
well, maybe like conditions where your mood
is negatively affecting your life, like
for example, a person
that suffers from anxiety.
That's right.
So some people have anxiety disorders.
And this means that they're
always worried about something.
Right.
So they're always anxious.
Always anxious.
So people who are
anxious often tap their
fingers or their pencils
or their foot, talk quickly.
So anxiety, it's not fun to feel
anxious and you can only imagine.
So a lot of times these
people who have anxiety
problems, they will
see their psychiatrist
and they will try and
get some medicines and
pills to help regulate their
emotions, to help them feel in control.
Okay.
So that I think is
the most interesting
thing for me is because
your mood is actually
very much dependent on what's
going on chemically in your body.
So as you said, you
could actually balance
out maybe if you're
feeling too anxious with
drugs, you can actually make you feel
less anxious because of the chemicals.
Exactly.
And it's also important to remember
that it's not just drugs that you take.
Sometimes people like to exercise and that
helps them feel relaxed and calm because
when you exercise actually,
your body produces certain
chemicals that help you
feel happy or when you eat.
Sometimes when you have an eaten,
you notice that you're very, very cranky.
Oh, God, why are you doing this?
Why are you being like this?
And you eat and all of
a sudden, oh, your body
chemistry starts to change
and so you feel better.
I heard that some
people that suffer from
anxiety disorders will be also
compulsive eaters because they're nervous.
So you notice that some
people eat when they're
nervous, this is one of the
side effects possibly, right?
It is.
I've heard this too,
that a lot of people who
are nervous or who are
anxious, they overeat.
I mean, they eat too much
even when they're not hungry.
Even when they're not
hungry and this actually
has a very large effect
on your body because
obviously you, like I said, your
body chemistry affects your mood.
So if you eat too
much, your body may be
reacts negatively and
you're even less happy.
Right, right.
It happens to me
sometimes in the movie
theater like a really
good scene or I'm nervous
or there's an action
sequence and I'm just
eating that popcorn up
and I'm not, I'm already
really, really thirsty but I
just can't stop that's funny.
So if you have any questions
or any other ways to describe
feelings, maybe you could post
them on our boards at EnglishPod.com.
There are so many different feelings
and most of them have words or names.
Look those up in your
dictionaries and let us know.
Alright, we'll see you guys then.
Bye.